<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://yazin.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://yazin.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-11-24T11:57:28+03:00</updated><id>https://yazin.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Yazin Alirhayim</title><subtitle>Muslim technology entrepeneur. Learn by doing.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">On Focus</title><link href="https://yazin.org/on-focus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Focus" /><published>2017-08-16T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-08-26T21:28:37+03:00</updated><id>https://yazin.org/on-focus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yazin.org/on-focus/">&lt;p&gt;Some people think that focus is the result or inherent perseverence, or the result of “passion” or some innate quality. I believe it’s the result of success. It’s much easier to focus on something, and persevere, when it’s working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of a lean startup, if you don’t encounter early signs of success, then it’s often best to give up and move on to the next thing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Some people think that focus is the result or inherent perseverence, or the result of “passion” or some innate quality. I believe it’s the result of success. It’s much easier to focus on something, and persevere, when it’s working.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Maverick And His Machine</title><link href="https://yazin.org/bookshelf/the-maverick-and-his-machine/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Maverick And His Machine" /><published>2017-05-28T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2020-11-24T11:57:18+03:00</updated><id>https://yazin.org/bookshelf/the-maverick-and-his-machine</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yazin.org/bookshelf/the-maverick-and-his-machine/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;lessons-learned&quot;&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, great book to read! Covers traditional 1900’s business and how it’s changed over the course of the next 50 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things I learned:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The importance of discovering, attaining, and then maintaining a monopoly. IBM did this exceptionally well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once a monopoly is attained, keep an eye peeled for potential future disruptors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The importance of having a carefully designed company culture from day one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notable-notes&quot;&gt;Notable Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attributes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avid networker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Watson had a system: a friendship apparatus run by his five secretaries. They kept files on every acquaintance, each file jammed with every letter and telegram exchanged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One key to the system was action; nothing could languish&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Family&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;According to Tom Jr., a major source of anguish was his sense that the awesome weight of this father was constantly bearing down on him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Worse, his father’s telegram seemed to mock him. His father had so little confidence in Tom that he rigged the system to Tom’s advantage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Away from the influence of his father, Tom discovered who he was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;competition&quot;&gt;Competition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;creating-a-monopoly&quot;&gt;Creating a monopoly&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the late 1980s, Patterson realized that NCR was creating its own competition problem. NCR was so good at making cash registers that the machines tended to last for years. Independent dealers started buying used cash registers from establishments that either went out of busniess or bought newer models. the dealers buffed them up and sold them, more often than not to someone who otherwise would have bought a new NCR machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what did they do? Watson went ahead and setup stores next to the existing used-register sellers, disguised as just another competitor. However,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;because Watson was backed by NCR and had no need to make a profit, he could pay more to get used cash registers and then sell them for less, both starving and undercutting all the competing stores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He wasn’t done there…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When the competing businesses started to crumble because of Watson’s pricing, Watson’s company, as a friendly gestuer, would offer a deal. He’d buy the business out, usually for more than was necessary, to prevent the owners from feeling railroaded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;monopoly-breeds-resistance-to-change&quot;&gt;Monopoly breeds resistance to change&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;IBM, though, had a huge legacy business to protect. In 1953, IBM brought in $497 million in revenue, and only $14 million of it came from electronic machines, mainly the 604 electronic calculator. The rest of the revenue came from punch card systems…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, the S-curve woes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;invest-in-rd&quot;&gt;Invest in R&amp;amp;D&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Somehow, [in the midst of the depression] Watson had to stimulate demand. He had to come up with products that companies couldn’t resist, whatever the economic conditions. Again, thanks to Charles Kettering’s influence, Watson believed that R&amp;amp;D would drive sales. So Watson decided to build a lab, pull engineers together, and get them charged up to push the technology forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;patents&quot;&gt;Patents&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The formula began with patents. Watson had learned the value of patents while at NCR and from Kettering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Controlling the key patents on tabulating systems helped make life difficult for the competition because competitors would have to invent entirely new technology or licence IBM’s patents, which IBM could refuse to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;culture&quot;&gt;Culture&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What Watson’s IBM did better than any company in the world was to create and manage a strong, choesive — and &lt;em&gt;successful&lt;/em&gt; — corporate culture. In turn, that culture wove together the pieces of the business and drove employees forward in ways that competitors couldn’t beat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;internal-competition&quot;&gt;Internal competition&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watson created rivalries among the internal groups at IBM, by assigning the work to multiple groups at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The groups competed ferociously, creating a sense of urgency &lt;strong&gt;even when the company controlled the market&lt;/strong&gt; and had virtually no outside competitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is very reminiscent of Bezos’s approach to teams at Amazon. However, it’s crucial to reward not just the winners but also the losers (which Watson did). Employees would write to him:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I know you have not looked upon my defects as evidence of incompetence, I shall strive harder to justify your good opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;business-savvy&quot;&gt;Business savvy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Watson turned to Bryce, and ordered him to assign his best engineer to figure out how to “gear down” the machines that the government and miliray would return after the war. The high-speed, top-of-the-line model were to go back out to customers operating at one-half or even one-tenth of their original speed. … IBM was going to market the old machines to smaller businesses that had never before been able to afford an IBM installation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alas, however, later in life he became resistant to change:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Watson had no reason to think customers would want to process data thousands of times faster. Customers seemed satisfied with the pace of IBM’s electromechanical machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alas, it sorta worked out in the end:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Watson met with Jim Bryce and Clair Lake, and ordered them to build a computer that would make Aiken’s current and future machines look like child’s toys. &lt;strong&gt;IBM got into electronics as an act of vengeance&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;evolution-after-watson-sr&quot;&gt;Evolution after Watson Sr.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;New ideas — Tom Jr’s ideas — percolated through IBM. Watsom had ong valued loyalty, devotion, and conformity. Tom Jr. valued imagination, professionalism, and individualism. Tom Jr. wanted more “wild ducks” as he called them — people who broke formation and took chances. The new ideas appealed to a high-flying postwar generation of workers who balked at blindly following orders and dressing alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a series of bad executive hires:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Opel and Akers simply did not have Watson coarsing through their veins. They both were supersmart, charming, clever executives but they had too little of Watson’s devotion to customers, his competitive hunger, and his willingness to bet big.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All too common in next-gen businesses (businesses that the original founder no longer runs).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Lessons learned</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Code</title><link href="https://yazin.org/bookshelf/code/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Code" /><published>2017-05-20T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-06-01T00:26:15+03:00</updated><id>https://yazin.org/bookshelf/code</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yazin.org/bookshelf/code/">&lt;p&gt;The never-say-die spirit once again, this time embodied in the form of Dan Colussy. It’s just amazing how you can — with considerable effort — bring together such a diverse group of people with such varying interests to achieve a given end goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Iridium satellites are operational to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notable-notes&quot;&gt;Notable Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Governments don’t like global things. We were stepping on toes”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently, even a company the size of Motorola can’t take on all the telecom companies across the world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The never-say-die spirit once again, this time embodied in the form of Dan Colussy. It’s just amazing how you can — with considerable effort — bring together such a diverse group of people with such varying interests to achieve a given end goal.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Profiles Of The Future</title><link href="https://yazin.org/bookshelf/profiles-of-the-future/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Profiles Of The Future" /><published>2017-05-15T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-06-01T00:26:15+03:00</updated><id>https://yazin.org/bookshelf/profiles-of-the-future</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yazin.org/bookshelf/profiles-of-the-future/"></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Eccentric Orbits</title><link href="https://yazin.org/bookshelf/eccentric-orbits/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Eccentric Orbits" /><published>2017-05-06T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-06-01T00:26:15+03:00</updated><id>https://yazin.org/bookshelf/eccentric-orbits</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yazin.org/bookshelf/eccentric-orbits/">&lt;p&gt;The never-say-die spirit once again, this time embodied in the form of Dan Colussy. It’s just amazing how you can — with considerable effort — bring together such a diverse group of people with such varying interests to achieve a given end goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Iridium satellites are operational to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notable-notes&quot;&gt;Notable Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Governments don’t like global things. We were stepping on toes”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently, even a company the size of Motorola can’t take on all the telecom companies across the world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The never-say-die spirit once again, this time embodied in the form of Dan Colussy. It’s just amazing how you can — with considerable effort — bring together such a diverse group of people with such varying interests to achieve a given end goal.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Never Split The Difference</title><link href="https://yazin.org/bookshelf/never-split-the-difference/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Never Split The Difference" /><published>2017-03-24T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-04-14T09:15:48+03:00</updated><id>https://yazin.org/bookshelf/never-split-the-difference</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yazin.org/bookshelf/never-split-the-difference/"></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Build Full Sized Plane</title><link href="https://yazin.org/teleport/logs/build-full-sized-plane/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Build Full Sized Plane" /><published>2017-03-16T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-04-20T00:20:46+03:00</updated><id>https://yazin.org/teleport/logs/build-full-sized-plane</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yazin.org/teleport/logs/build-full-sized-plane/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve started work on building the full-sized MyTwinDream that I received last week. This plane is HUGE and I can easily see how it can carry several kilograms of payload for delivery, in addition to the loads of batteries it’ll need to go long range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I &lt;a href=&quot;/teleport/logs/mini-waypoint-attempt-6/&quot;&gt;no longer have the Pixhawk&lt;/a&gt;, I’ll be using a Pixracer (a newer, smaller version of the original Pixhawk). I’ll also be using a custom battery pack made from the LiIon cells I’d developed previously (but were too heavy to include in the smaller AXN).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Installed and centered all of the control surfaces&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Installed the airspeed sensor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Got the GPS working&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/fullsize-gps-working.png&quot; alt=&quot;GPS working&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update (March 17):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Connected control surfaces to flight controller&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Installed the radio receiver&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth noting that this is a fairly large plane — definitely the largest I’ve built to date. I’ve also got huge 11 inch propellers installed on the dual motors, so we’re talking about huge amounts of thrust!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some progress pics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/cables-inside-hull.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cables everywhere&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/motor-mount.png&quot; alt=&quot;Motor mount&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/plane-not-complete.png&quot; alt=&quot;Plane in progress&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also finally received the other 40A ESC I was waiting for (I only had one), so now I can test the whole plane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be working on the Lithium Ion battery pack once I receive the copper rod I’ve ordered in order to make my own spot welder. I tried to find one in the nearby university, but they didn’t have one (strange!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update (March 20):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I went ahead and calibrated all of the RC channels. I also centered all of the servos and got them setup properly. I attempted to connect the analog airspeed sensor that I had previously used on the Pixhawk (by connecting it to the ADC port). The Pixracer does &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rcgroups.com/forums/showthread.php?2576614-Pixracer-Autopilot-the-new-PIXHAWK-generation-is-available/page149&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; support the Analog airspeed sensor, so I ordered a digital one instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than that, I’m currently waiting on the Power Distribution Board with a built-in BEC that can output both 5V and 12V (I’ll need the 12V for the LED strips on the planes wings so I can see it in the dark).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was hopeful I’ll be able to get a used car battery so I can do the spot welding of the Lithium Ion battery pack, but I tried a few nearby places and turned out short. I’m now searching for alternative high current sources (600A+). If all else fails, I’ll just solder the battery terminals directly (though I risk damaging the cells that way).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update (March 22):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I received the Power Distribution Module (with the built-in 5V/12V BEC) — that means I’m all set to get the plane ready for its maiden flight!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a run down of the things I’ve done today:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added the landing gear. Wasn’t going to do this at first, but this would be perfect for full autonomy — I can now set it up to takeoff on its own, without even me having to hand-launch it!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Calibrated the ESCs. To do this, I had to fashion a Y-cable that connects both motor control signals to a single servo lead that I plug into the flight controller. Tested, and it worked perfectly. Motors are now both in perfect sync.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Connected the Power Distribution Module to the ESCs and the flight controller. I’m using the Pixhawk power module (which has a built-in 5V BEC that I’m using solely for the flight controller). This feeds the current and voltage metered data to the flight controller for monitoring. All other electronics are being powered by the BEC on the power distribution module.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/plane-landing-gear.png&quot; alt=&quot;Landing gear&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/plane-internal-wiring.png&quot; alt=&quot;Internal wiring&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/plane-pdm.png&quot; alt=&quot;Power Distribution Module&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that remains now is to connect the camera &amp;amp; on-screen display up — and put together the Li-Ion battery pack (this is going to be a massive 23,000mAh 4S pack that weighs over 1kg). Should keep it in the air for several hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update (March 23 &amp;amp; 24)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setup Bluetooth telemetry &lt;a href=&quot;http://diydrones.com/profiles/blogs/connecting-your-phone-tablet-or-laptop-to-apm-pixhawk-using-bluet&quot;&gt;using this excellent guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Connected and installed the LEDs on the underside of the wings so that I can spot the plane in the dark. Right = green, Left = red. Nice and bright! They’re being fed 12V from the power distribution board.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; able to get the servo outputs of the Pixracer to work. I opened several support requests but to no avail. Looks like I just got a faulty Pixracer. The issue is that the servo outputs are supposed to reflect the RC inputs when the vehicle is ARMed and set to MANUAL mode. They don’t. Even the MAVlink messages show the purported servo outputs correctly, but I just get 0 on the outputs. I hooked up an Arduino to Channel 1 of the servo outputs to verify, and confirmed the 0 reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expected servo output:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/expected-servo-output.png&quot; alt=&quot;Expected servo output&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actual servo output:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/actual-servo-output.png&quot; alt=&quot;Actual servo output&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A whole lotta nothingness! Of course, without servo outputs the plane can’t fly. That means I’ll have to get the Pixracer replaced (and God knows how long that’s going to take to happen). In the mean time, I’m going to have to fallback to whatever flight controller I have handy — which means the APM2.8. It’s my last hope. Will have to replace all of the Pixracer connectors with the APM connectors and try again 😫&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update (19 Apr):&lt;/strong&gt; I’ve been spending the past 2 weeks preparing for technical interviews at various companies. I’ll have a more in-depth post on this in the near future, but for now I’ve had little time for anything else. I plan on resuming this project in the first week of May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve started work on building the full-sized MyTwinDream that I received last week. This plane is HUGE and I can easily see how it can carry several kilograms of payload for delivery, in addition to the loads of batteries it’ll need to go long range.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Losing 100g everyday</title><link href="https://yazin.org/experiments/lose-100g-a-day/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Losing 100g everyday" /><published>2017-03-15T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2020-11-15T17:58:23+03:00</updated><id>https://yazin.org/experiments/lose-100g-a-day</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yazin.org/experiments/lose-100g-a-day/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-experiment&quot;&gt;The experiment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world of weight loss is a very complicated one. There’s all sorts of diets, plans and routines that you’re supposed to follow — and frankly, a large element of nonsense too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it doesn’t have to be. I mean, let’s consider a first principles approach to weight loss. Picture the human body as a lump of energy. According to the law of conservation of energy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the total energy of an isolated system remains constant—it is said to be conserved over time. &lt;strong&gt;Energy can neither be created nor destroyed; rather, it transforms from one form to another.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our bodies are not isolated systems — we have energy coming in (when we eat/drink) and energy going out (for basic metabolism, exercise, etc.). However, if we just track both of those things, we should be able to accurately control the weight we lose / gain (since weight &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; energy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of this approach, if it works, is that you can eat whatever you want. Bite the fatty backside of a bison if you like, a calorie is a calorie! Instead of focusing on the type of food, we focus on the caloric content (which is more directly influenced by the portion size).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Track the energy coming into your body (calories in), and the energy going out (calories out)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure more energy is going out than coming in (by at least 100g/day)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That’s it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setup&quot;&gt;Setup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I found my Basal Metabolic Rate (BMR). That’s how many calories I’ll burn a day even if I never get out of bed. It’s the energy my body consumes to stay alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find your BMR, you can use the formula (which I got from &lt;a href=&quot;https://bmi-calories.com/bmr-calculator.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;BMR = 88.362 + (13.397 * Weight_{kg}) + (4.799 * Height_{cm}) - (5.677 * Age)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mine turned out to be 1,830 calories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so the nett calorie count for the day \(Cal_{nett}\) is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Cal_{nett} = Cal_{in} - Cal_{out} - BMR&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I convert \(Cal_{nett}\) into grams by dividing by 9, since 1g of fat is equivalent to 9 calories. That tells me how much weight I lost on a particular day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this does assume that your body absorbs 100% of the calories you eat, which is not true. The calories you eat represent a ceiling — but a good chunk of the food you eat doesn’t get absorbed, and well - passes right through!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming an absorption ratio of 95% (or 0.95):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Cal_{nett} = Cal_{in} * 0.95 - Cal_{out} - BMR&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, the math lesson is over 😄&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I created a Google Sheet to calculate all this automatically:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/experiments/weight-loss-settings-sheet.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google Sheet with Settings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to make this all easier to track, I also setup a Google Form which I used to fill in the calories I consume/use every day:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/experiments/weight-loss-tracker.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google form for tracking weight loss&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(You can download both the Sheet &amp;amp; Form &lt;a href=&quot;#below&quot;&gt;below&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everytime I eat something (or do some exercise), I log it in … and the sheet is updated automatically. At the end of the day, I throttle my calorie consumption to ensure that there’s always a net loss of 100g or so of body weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rules&quot;&gt;Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Log all incoming and outgoing energy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stop eating once you’ve hit a 100g deficit for a particular day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;update-1-month&quot;&gt;Update: 1 month&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow, this experiment has worked better than I could’ve ever imagined! Checkout the results below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/experiments/weight-loss-results-1-month.png&quot; alt=&quot;Results after 1 month&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expected weight is 75.0kg as of today, but my actual weight (when I first wake up in the morning) is 74.5kg!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/experiments/weight-loss-results-1-month-actual.png&quot; alt=&quot;Actual weight&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s insane — it means I’m actually losing &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; than 100g each day, since I’ve lost 3.3kg to date (in just 30 days).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to keep this experiment going for another month or so until I hit the 70kg range, which I think would be ideal. I’ll make sure to share more details around the specifics of how I accomplished this, and tips you can use to do the same once I’ve got a firm grip of things (say in a month or so).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;below&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;now-you-can-do-this-too&quot;&gt;Now, you can do this too!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I’m such a great guy, I’m sharing the Google Form &amp;amp; Google Sheet templates that I used to track my progress:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;👉 &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/1bXvxypWbJ3iIjskVOsa7IHGkxrgQ7xCP?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Link to Google Form &amp;amp; Sheet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use this yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Copy the Form and Sheet to your own Google Drive folder&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Update the Settings in the “⚙️” sheet to include your own details&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start tracking calories, and observe your progress in the “Summary” sheet!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you found this useful, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/yazinsai&quot;&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">After several recent vacations (and food binges). I've always thought small changes done regularly are better than big changes done occasionally. So here's my take on it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Triumph Of Genius</title><link href="https://yazin.org/bookshelf/a-triumph-of-genius/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Triumph Of Genius" /><published>2017-02-28T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-03-29T10:35:03+03:00</updated><id>https://yazin.org/bookshelf/a-triumph-of-genius</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yazin.org/bookshelf/a-triumph-of-genius/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;lessons-learned&quot;&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good thing Land didn’t get too enamored with the polarized vehicle headlights idea to pursue anything else. That’s important when building fundamentally new technology — the potential applications should not be dictated by you, but by the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also … God, is litigation slow! Kodak’s case vs. Polaroid took 14 years to resolve. 14 years!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;highlights&quot;&gt;Highlights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A lifelong motto was: “If anything is worth doing, it’s worth doing to excess.” Land had learned early on that total engrossment was the best way for him to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“An education without a degree?” Wheelwright told him that he didn’t think the degree mattered. Land gradually concurred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;He rented a room on the sunny side of the hotel and arrived carrying nothing but a bowl full of goldfish. When the American Optical representative came to the room, Land showed him the bowl, which he had placed on a windowsill in the full glare of sunlight. “Can you see any fish?” Land asked. Of course, the man could not—until Land held a piece of polarized material in front of the fishbowl. The American Optical executive, who had seen every version of sunglasses on the market, exclaimed that “he had never seen anything like this.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Show it. don’t explain it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Land employed a unique strategy for identifying good employment prospects. “I don’t care what the people know if they’re willing to work hard,” he once told Wheelwright, “and they consider it a pleasure to come here and work.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Land had a penchant for bringing a variety of eclectic and unorthodox thinkers to Polaroid, giving them the basic equipment they needed for their research without much fretting about the short-term payoff, and just turning them loose for long periods of time. . . . Land generally left them alone, waiting for them to call him, or calling them in when he had a short term project that needed their special skills. This provided fertile ground for new ideas that might come to the fore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like &lt;a href=&quot;/bookshelf/dealers-of-lightning/&quot;&gt;Xerox PARC&lt;/a&gt;. Like &lt;a href=&quot;/bookshelf/i-invented-the-modern-age/&quot;&gt;Ford&lt;/a&gt;. They are on to something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As Land ultimately recognized, the adoption of his system was fatally hampered by the fact that there was no competitive advantage for any car company in using it first. Since all cars needed to incorporate the technology as simultaneously as possible, it was either going to be all, either voluntarily or as directed by the government, or none.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No network effects kick off without the initial intrinsic benefit&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Indeed, one of Land’s great strengths as a scientist, one that made him virtually indefatigable, was his understanding that to research necessarily meant to endure without discouragement the “error” part of the “trial and error” axiom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is crucial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Land had him pose and then took his photograph. He turned the crank and out came the sandwich of negative and positive. In a minute, Land peeled away the print, showed it to the audience, and handed it to the president. According to McCune, “It astonished everybody . . . everyone went wild.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the one-step camera “appealed to Americans’ innate love for instant gratification.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Th&amp;gt; e journey from the moment in Santa Fe when his daughter asked her pivotal question to a credible demonstration for Eastman Kodak was achieved in just over two years, while the full commercialization occurred in less than five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;impressive even by todays standards&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An art student of Land’s friend, Clarence Kennedy, she had absolutely no scientific training. Yet she apparently had the right stuff for Land and excelled in his laboratory under the tutelage and inspiration he provided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;According to Rogers, Morse emulated Land’s laboratory style, which was to propose the hypothesis, to test the hypothesis, to modify the hypothesis, to test with another experiment—[the investigation proceeding like] a sequential train moving at high speed, several hypotheses and experiments per hour. And yet the environment was calm. The results seemed more like the magical growing of a plant in time-lapse pictures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“My first ambition [for my one-step film was] neither to wash it nor to use a print coater,” Land later confessed.64 However, while inconvenient, the print coater turned out to be hugely effective, providing black-and-white prints that proved perfectly stable for decades. Customers accepted the procedure without complaint, and thus “the first and only real crisis in sixty-second photography” was averted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sympathetic customers are a key pre indicator of a product’s success&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Land’s “aim was to produce the most perfect picture-making process, and he felt that I, an exacting photographer, could provide important feedback. Since I balanced creative ideals with a practical approach, were I pleased with his product, so too might other creative and professional photographers.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feedback loop&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think whether outside science or within science there is no such thing as group originality or group creativity or group perspicacity. I do believe wholeheartedly in the individual capacity for greatness. . . . Profundity and originality are attributes of single, if not singular, minds. Two minds may sometimes be better than one, provided that each of the two minds is working separately while the two are working together; yet three tend to become a crowd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Consistent with his philosophy of “turning his people loose [on scientific investigations] for long periods of time,”1 Land had allowed Rogers to work without any interference for almost six years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow. Just, wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the 1970s, Land convinced President Nixon to authorize the Keyhole 11 space satellite, one that used a space telescope aimed at earth to provide the finest intelligence pictures yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos from above, 45 years ago!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To find a solution, Land moved up to Rogers’ laboratory and, with a small group of people, “went at it day and night.”90 Early on the morning after Labor Day in 1962, Land called Mervis and asked him to come to the laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow (again)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;film—the elimination of the need for a print coater—was a clear example of Land’s indefatigable attitude toward research. “Almost every day . . . we took on things which people might think would take a year or two,” he said. “They weren’t particularly hard. What was hard was believing they weren’t hard.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“One thing about Land—when he is doing something wild and risky, he is careful to insulate himself from anyone who’s critical. It’s very easy in the early stages to have a dream exploded.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testimony to the importance of isolation of negative feedback. Sometimes it’s important (coming from customers) and sometimes it’s detrimental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We designed the camera as if we had solved the problem, and carried the camera all the way through engineering while doing the basic research on the chemical task of bringing the picture directly into the light.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When asked later how he could have taken such a risk—having committed to a camera design and to building manufacturing facilities before a final solution to the project’s greatest challenge had been found—Land reminded a reporter of one of his basic tenets, steeped in his personal brand of indefatigable confidence: “If you can state a problem, then you can solve it. From then on it’s just hard work.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Land was no longer simply an ingenious inventor and customer; he was an enlarging and possibly troublesome competitor.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Although Kodak was aware that the “license agreement [they received] was not really going to be meaningful” because it covered technology that was “rapidly going to be obsolete,” Petersen had convinced Eilers to let him pursue it “as a matter of pride.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Moving quickly, he brought a small number of engineers, including Wareham, together into a room in his Osborn Street facility and joined with them to tackle the problems with the camera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never afraid to pull up his sleeves and get busy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As Wareham later recalled with a grin, Land said, “You’re allowed one engineering failure and you’ve just had it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dr. Land had an uncanny way of making an individual an expert by telling him that it was his job to be that expert, that important decisions would depend on the results of his work, and that the results were needed quickly. Yet the intensity of the work was balanced by good humor, by intervals of celebration, by time taken to contemplate technical and social consequences on all sides, and by the sense that the work was a shared responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Polaroid, led by the charismatic and enigmatic Land, had become the Apple Computer of the mid-twentieth century. It was arguably the most admired and glamorous technology company in the world. A loyal fan base of consumers and investors eagerly anticipated its new products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We don’t do market surveys. We create the markets with our products.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The supreme confidence underlying Land’s decision to move ahead had always been his singular attribute, and in many ways the real secret to all of his and Polaroid’s success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;conducted a press conference prior to the start of the meeting. As reported by an observer, Land took the podium and casually took a “smallish camera out of his pocket, held it aloft and put it back in his pocket.”14 That was it. He did not demonstrate its operation; he didn’t even open it.15 He did comment, however: “The way it opens is unprecedented and is a delight.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Steve Jobs, an admitted Land disciple, at his company’s annual meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s where Steve Jobs got his flair :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Land was just following his basic equation: more secrecy created more mystery, and that, in turn, created more excitement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Land acknowledged that the initial peel-apart system was but a stepping stone towards his idealized concept, admitting that Polaroid’s first system “didn’t quite make it as you know, although we did do well enough to keep our company going and growing, well enough so that we had the luxury during the last ten years of going back to the full-grown dream of a system in which all you did was look at the image in your finder, press a button, have something come out through a pair of steel rollers, and end up with a dry, finished, shiny, beautiful picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medium term solution to fund long term goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was an elegant system of camera and film that the Kodak engineers ultimately dubbed “a masterpiece of engineering.” It was readily apparent to all that Polaroid’s system was far superior to the product Kodak had in development at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Kodak’s marketing executives were forced to admit the obvious: “We see no unique consumer benefits in the proposed Kodak program at this time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a situation! im dying to know what happened next&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In apparent desperation, a KPDC memo directed Kodak engineers to “not be constrained by what an individual feels is a potential patent infringement.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh no you didn’t Kodak (they did.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Even though Polaroid experienced some bugs in the SX-70 as 1973 began, as Bill McCune later explained, the introduction continued because “we felt it was important to get the product on the market as rapidly as possible so that we would learn from the customer’s use of it and from the marketing aspects and customer service.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But Land had little interest in such a system, preferring the elegance of the leather-encased, fully automated folding SX-70 camera made of metal, not plastic.14 Although some development work was conducted at Polaroid toward a more economical model, Land did not consider it a priority at this juncture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snap up the high end of the market while you can&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The breadth and intensity of Polaroid’s research over the years thus resulted in a correspondingly comprehensive collection of patents covering both the technology embodied in its commercial SX-70 system and alternative approaches to many of the key camera and film features. Polaroid regarded this as a legitimate intellectual property strategy for securing the fruits of its labors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Kodak’s announced willingness to license other companies to manufacture cameras that would use Kodak’s film, something that Polaroid had never done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kodak vs Polaroid.. Microsoft vs Apple. The parallels in their approach to market domination are uncanny. Polaroid focused on price, Kodak on volume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Polaroid’s longtime mentor had become its archenemy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Polaroid was selling more cameras now than it had been before Kodak introduced its competing products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Land resisted providing simple and straightforward answers to even simple questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The incongruity was inescapable between the testimony this expert had just given for almost two weeks, belittling so many mechanical features of the SX-70, and his previous views on the same camera, published before he had been retained as a hired gun to testify for Kodak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Land had always had a problem in praising colleagues directly and personally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A few years later, immersed in pure research, and having authored a stack of scholarly scientific publications, Land proclaimed that at the Rowland Institute he was “now living out the dream I have had since I was seventeen years old.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;After three and a half years of deliberation, and nine and a half years after the case was filed, Judge Rya Zobel broke perhaps another record by finally announcing her decision in the landmark case of Polaroid Corporation v. Eastman Kodak Company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It is worth noting . . . that the harm Kodak will suffer simply mirrors the success it has enjoyed in the field of instant photography. As one court has observed,” she wrote, “the infringer ‘should not be heard to complain’ when it loses its gamble and reaps predictable results.”11&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;After Polaroid also threatened to appeal, the two parties, at long last, settled the case for $925 million (more than $1.6 billion in 2014 dollars) on July 16, 1991.14 It was fifteen years, three months, and twenty days after the lawsuit had begun. The final award was much less than Polaroid had sought and much more than Kodak thought it should pay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Kodak elected to go forward nonetheless because management believed that through its patent clearance process—which, incidentally and perhaps conveniently, had found not a single Polaroid patent that Kodak might have infringed to be valid—they had “managed the risk to a low level.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Polaroid remained wedded to the technology it had pioneered and reportedly “turned down flat” an offer to partner with Japan’s Hitachi Ltd. on its version of a filmless camera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alas, they missed the next bus&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As Land liked to say, “Every creative act is a sudden cessation of stupidity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Jobs admiringly assured Land that in building Apple, he had tried to emulate the ideals Land had described to him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Lessons learned</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mini Waypoint Attempt 6</title><link href="https://yazin.org/teleport/logs/mini-waypoint-attempt-6/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mini Waypoint Attempt 6" /><published>2017-02-27T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-03-14T02:27:44+03:00</updated><id>https://yazin.org/teleport/logs/mini-waypoint-attempt-6</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yazin.org/teleport/logs/mini-waypoint-attempt-6/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-plane-build&quot;&gt;New plane build&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, I had a spare AXN on hand so I immediately got busy building it again (something I can now do in my sleep!). I decided to add in an FPV (First Person View) camera gear on the plane so that I can see what’s going on at all times. I’m also going to be painting it bright colors, and adding a buzzer for an alarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still want to give the APM a chance, but something tells me that I’ll be better off moving to the Pixhawk PX4, or the &lt;a href=&quot;http://seriouslypro.com/spracingf3&quot;&gt;SP F3 controller&lt;/a&gt;. I really want to get this tried and tested before my full-scale plane arrives (sometime early next week!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to move quickly, but with zero tolerance for mistakes — certainly not ones I’ve done before (and there are plenty by now).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;changes-from-previous-models&quot;&gt;Changes from previous models&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m making quite a few changes from the previous models I’ve built to date … many prompted in an attempt to reduce the risk of the plane getting lost:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adding camera gear for FPV flying&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Painting it a really bright color (so I can see it in the sky)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adding buzzer so I can find it when it crashes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add telemetry so I can get plane information at my remote control&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Swapped the AXN motor for the Turnigy 2730-1300 (I don’t have a spare AXN on hand)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Configure failsafe on the transmitter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I’ll be following many of the best practices listed &lt;a href=&quot;http://beta.ivc.no/wiki/index.php/AXN_Clouds_Fly_Setup&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-build&quot;&gt;The Build&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I spent most of the day setting up the Seriously Pro F3 board to work as the autopilot of choice for this flight. Thankfully, I was able to get the GPS working early on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/inav-working-gps.png&quot; alt=&quot;GPS working on SP F3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I later started with the actual setup, including all the configuration for the RC, the calibration and everything else. I also painted it, though I ran out of spray paint after finishing the underbody:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/spray-painted-mini-body.png&quot; alt=&quot;Painted the plane body&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made the right side of the wing neon-green so I can tell which direction it’s facing when it’s in the air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update 2-Mar&lt;/strong&gt;: Today, I configured the INAV and it’s all set for a test flight. I also added the video camera and transmitter, as well as setup the video ground station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pix below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/mini-fpv-camera.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mini FPV camera&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/mini-fpv-screen.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mini FPV screen&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow, I’ll take everything out for a spin … if it works well, will go ahead and run the waypoint flight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flight-with-f3&quot;&gt;Flight with F3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test flight did not go well, and I continually suffered with getting the F3 to ARM with the GPS in place. I finally relented and removed the GPS, since the initial flight was not going to be using the GPS modes anyway (I just wanted to get the thing trimmed and stable). When I threw it up in the air, I found that it wasn’t stable at all (despite being in Stabilize mode).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried once more with similar results. I’m sure I probably could’ve got the damn thing to work with a bit more fiddling about but I felt like I’d wasted too much time switching between platforms and trying to re-learn them. Instead, I decided I’d just go back to either the APM or Pixhawk — let’s hope we make quicker progress that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pixhawk-px4-configuration&quot;&gt;Pixhawk PX4 configuration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Switched to Pixhawk. Had to setup with the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I was using an &lt;strong&gt;analog&lt;/strong&gt; airspeed sensor connected to the ADC at the bottom right corner of the board. In order to get QGroundcontrol to recognize it, I had to &lt;a href=&quot;https://pixhawk.org/help/aspd&quot;&gt;set the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SENS_DPRES_ANSC = 1000&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the end, the sensor was too heavy so I had to remove it (and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pixhawk.org/firmware/parameters#circuit_breaker&quot;&gt;disable it&lt;/a&gt; by setting &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CBRK_AIRSPD_CHK = 162128&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I took it out for a test flight:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/pixhawk-flight-attempt-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pixhawk flight ready&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/pixhawk-flight.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pixhawk flight ready&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I originally set it up in just Stabilize mode, and it flew really well despite 30km/h winds. Alas, I flew it too low and crashed into a tree breaking off half the right wing. Thankfully, it was nothing a bit of UHU Por couldn’t handle. The bigger problem was getting the Pixhawk to stay in place — it’s always challenging getting it to sit tight in a foam plane. I’ve tried double-sided tape but it comes loose after almost any crash — no matter how minor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flight controllers (and the Pixhawk especially) are incredbily sensitive to axis turns. Finding a wayto mount it in a tight spot like the one I have in the AXN is an ongoing struggle — though it won’t be as big an issue in the full-scale MTD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having got these basic modes working, I proceeded to setup some &lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.px4.io/concept-flight-modes.html#flight-mode-quick-summary&quot;&gt;GPS-assisted modes&lt;/a&gt;. I used Position (which essentially maintains the same heading and altitude at neutral input) and Loiter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never did get a chance to try Loiter, but the Position flight worked like a charm. I had a few rough landings though in the high wind, and this meant the PX4 kept nudging about — until I eventually called it a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow, I’ll attempt Waypoint flight on the Pixhawk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;test-waypoint-flight&quot;&gt;Test waypoint flight&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I configured the Pixhawk using Qgroundcontrol. I don’t have an SD card handy, so I can’t use the onboard logging capability on the Pixhawk (It’ll be a few days before I get the one I ordered). Still, we’re going ahead anyway and hope everything works as expected. I’d like to have Telemetry on the plane so I can see how it’s progressing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made a few mods before the flight:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I installed a balsa wood base below the Pixhawk to keep it stable. I just used UHU Por to glue it in place, with the battery underneath. I should still be able to charge the battery without removing it, since the balance connector lies above the board. I also added some aluminum foil to the base to protect from interference to the magentometer resulting from the power lines underneath. I attached the Pixhawk to the board using double sided foam tape, which would double as a vibration dampener.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/balsa-wood-base.png&quot; alt=&quot;Balsa wood base&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Noticed that the frame was broken from the underside, so my faithful tube of UHU Por was summoned once again — it didn’t fail me.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I also followed every item on the pre-flight checklist, which was good because I found the magnetometer calibratoin to be off and the prop unbalanced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried setting up the waypoints for GPS flight but it turns out it needs the SD card too (which I don’t have on hand). I ordered one off Amazon and should be getting it tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/configured-waypoints.png&quot; alt=&quot;Configured waypoints in QGroundcontrol&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/waypoint-6-attempt.png&quot; alt=&quot;Waypoint attempt 6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already had the plane ready, so I took it out for a spin to test the non-GPS flight modes again. It flew really well — and I was having so much fun that I forgot about the battery until I tried bringing the plane back from a field about 500m away. It seems to have run out of battery half-way through its journey, ultimately crashing on a side road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked up the pieces and brought it home — the 3S battery was at just 8.4V (that’s 2.8V/cell)! The minimum voltage for a LiPo cell before you start getting irreversible damage is 3.2V/cell. I went straight home to recharge it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The battery is rated at 850mAh but it was so drained that it charged all the way up to 908mAh:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/waypoint-6-crash.png&quot; alt=&quot;Waypoint attempt 6 - crash&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/battery.png&quot; alt=&quot;Battery i'm using&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/waypoint-battery-charged.png&quot; alt=&quot;Battery charged at higher than rated!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll fix the plane now, in preparation for tomorrow’s &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; GPS waypoint flight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; Attempted to launch this baby today (March 7) but the GPS wasn’t working, and I still hadn’t received the SD card. I ended up replacing the NEO-M8N with the previously working NEO-7M (this is the second GPS I’ve now replaced in a week, so our friends in China obviously seem to be having some serious quality issues). By the time I got the SD card and replaced everything out, it was dark. Will launch first thing tomorrow morning inshallah!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update2 :&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attempted to fly today early morning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/waypoint-6-early.png&quot; alt=&quot;Early morning flight&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was super wet. I fired up the plane in AUTO made and threw it in the air. It was supposed to auto-start the motor and take off, but it did not. Looks like there’s some special configuration I’ll need to do to the Pixhawk to make it automatically take off. Instead, I decided I’d launch it in Stabilize mode, gain altitude and then switch to Auto mode. I was able to take off, and once I switched to AUTO the plane did change course towards the first waypoint. However, it struggled with the wind, and just kept lost altitude until eventually crashing into the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went back to the workshop with the following changes in mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setup auto takeoff.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reorient the waypoints considering the wind direction. I should launch into the wind (i.e. upwind) and land upwind as well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Secure the battery in place, since it seemed to have come off after the crash landing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intent not to waste more time, I went right to it — finding out early on that there’s a TAKEOFF waypoint type that I should be using instead of just the standard WAYPOINT. That takes care of the first item. When it came time to update the waypoints I noticed that I wasn’t able to write the updated waypoints to the Pixhawk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a lot of fumbling about, I realized that this worked well in Arduplane but not on the Pixhawk firmware:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/pixhawk-config-issue.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pixhawk firmware unresponsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I switched to Arduplane and had to recalibrate everything, and setup the correct parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These params are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;TKOFF_THR_MINACC = 10&lt;/code&gt; (m/s/s, acceleration for hand launched plane)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;TKOFF_THR_DELAY = 2&lt;/code&gt; (s/10, delay before triggering motor in tenths of a second)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;TKOFF_THR_MINSPD = 3&lt;/code&gt; (m/s, groundspeed before motor is engaged)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;TECS_PITCH_MAX = 25&lt;/code&gt; (deg, this is the maximum pitch angle it’ll use when climbing)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then checked the control surface directions, and had to reverse the RC channels for Aileron and Rudder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After updating the flight modes to Stabilize, Loiter and Auto (i’m using a 3 position switch on my transmitter for controlling flight mode), I was ready to update the waypoints, which I promptly did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, to fly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went out, this time finally having made sure that it would work well. Everything was setup … I did a final check of all the control surfaces, and it worked great. I armed the motor and started increasing the throttle. Nothing. That’s weird. Tried again, this time checking to make sure the throttle was OK. Still nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did a few checks using the Tower app on my phone (connected to the bluetooth module that I connected to the Telemetry port on the Pixhawk). Everything was armed and OK. I took it back to the workshop and found the ESC to be faulty:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/faulty-esc.png&quot; alt=&quot;Faulty ESC&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh great. I replaced it, and it was dark — now to wait patiently until the morning for the test flight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update 3&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/projects/teleport/waypoint-7.png&quot; alt=&quot;Attempt X&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take off was perfect (right into the wind), and first 3 waypoints flew perfectly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The next few waypoints it struggled with, especially when it had to go against the wind. Eventually, the wind got faster than the plane itself and it started sliding backwards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After a few minutes, it crashed and lost. I know, i know. I had no FPV, no Telemetry and no GPS coordinates. I didn’t even have a buzzer on it so I could locate it by ear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QARcVOCR7tY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the plane did disappear, I consider the mission a partial success.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">New plane build Luckily, I had a spare AXN on hand so I immediately got busy building it again (something I can now do in my sleep!). I decided to add in an FPV (First Person View) camera gear on the plane so that I can see what’s going on at all times. I’m also going to be painting it bright colors, and adding a buzzer for an alarm.</summary></entry></feed>